<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An appendix to The history of independency being a brief description of some few of Argyle's proceedings, before and since he joyned in confederacy with the independent junto in England : with a parallel betwixt him and Cromwell, and a caveat to all his seduced adherents.</title>
            <title>History of independency. Appendix</title>
            <author>Walker, Clement, 1595-1651.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66797</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W321</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205122</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11821900</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11821900</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49589</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66797)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49589)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 555:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An appendix to The history of independency being a brief description of some few of Argyle's proceedings, before and since he joyned in confederacy with the independent junto in England : with a parallel betwixt him and Cromwell, and a caveat to all his seduced adherents.</title>
                  <title>History of independency. Appendix</title>
                  <author>Walker, Clement, 1595-1651.</author>
                  <author>Walker, Clement, 1595-1651. Relations and observations, historical and politick, upon the Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Royston ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by Clement Walker. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>An earlier edition appeared in the author's Relations and observations, historical, and political upon the Parliament.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Argyll, Archibald Campbell, --  Marquis of, 1598-1661.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49589:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49589:1"/>
            <p>AN APPENDIX TO <hi>The Hiſtory of Independency,</hi> BEING A brief deſcription of ſome few of AR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GYLE'S proceedings, before and ſince he joyned in Confederacy with the <hi>Independent Junto in</hi> ENGLAND: <hi>With a Parallel betwixt him and</hi> Cromwell, AND A Caveat to all his ſeduced Adherents.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>CICERO.</hi>
               </bibl> Totius injuſtitiae nulla capitalior eſt quam eorum, qui cum maximè fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunt, id tamen agunt, ut viri boni eſſe videantur.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Royſton,</hi> at the Angel in <hi>Ivie-lane.</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb facs="tcp:49589:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49589:2"/>
            <head>AN APPENDIX TO <hi>The Hiſtory of Independency.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>BEING A brief deſcription of ſome few of <hi>Argyle</hi>'s pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, before and ſince he joyned in confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracy with the <hi>Independent Junto</hi> in <hi>ENGLAND: With a Parallel betwixt him and</hi> Cromwell; AND A Caveat to all his ſeduced Adherents.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Covenant</hi> being at the firſt taking, held to be the true Touchſtone whereby the Religious Royal Subjects were diſcerned from all thoſe who were unwilling to ſubmit to the yoke of Chriſt in matters of Religion, or to the juſt and lawfull Government of our dread Soveraign his Vicegerent; now a ſubtil generation of men (or rather Vipers) in both Kingdomes, who did take the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and did magnifie it ſo long as it could ſerve them for a Lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to mount to their intended Greatneſs, being now at the top, have kick'd away the Ladder, and ſtanding (as it were) on the pinacle, look with diſdain on all their old friends, who out of the integrity of their hearts, did for the good of Religion, and His Majeſties honour, joyn in that ſolemn engagement, it being
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49589:3"/>far from their thoughts that their modeſt and humble deſires for the Reformation of ſome abuſes both in Church and State (all which, His Majeſty in the reſpective Kingdoms did (or was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to) cure) ſhould have ſtruck ſo deep as to endeavour the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow of all lawfull Governments, Civil and Eccleſiaſtical; bringing, inſtead of a promiſed Reformation in Religion, a curſed Toleration of the moſt damnable Sects, Errors, and Hereſies that ever Hell did ſend forth; and for the Civil State, inſtead of a well-ſetled Monarchy, a moſt confuſed tyrannical Anarchy, quite contrary to the words and meaning of the Covenant, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt intentions of all true-hearted, Religious and loyal Subjects in the three Kingdoms, who did take that ſolemn Covenant with a purpoſe to keep it, and of very many thouſands who did never take the Covenant, (yet very good Proteſtants and loyal Subjects) being more affrighted with the compulſory way of enforcing it on all, then unſatisfied in the matter, being introduced in a legal way, none of theſe deſerving the name of Malignants, or to be ſo cruelly dealt with either for their perſons or Eſtates, as hath been too too common in both Kingdoms; but the Covenant it ſelf, doth beſt decypher who are Incendiaries, Malignants, and evil Inſtruments, <hi>viz.</hi> thoſe who hinder the reformation of Religion, who divide the King from His People, or one Kingdom from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or make any Faction or Parties amongſt the people, contrary to the League and Covenant: Yet by our new tenets, none muſt be called Malignants but thoſe that have loyal hearts towards their Soveraign, though otherwiſe never ſo Religious, and all of them (with Maſter <hi>Martin</hi>) would gladly make the <hi>Covenant an old Almanack,</hi> that they might be rid of that tie of <hi>preſerving His Majeſties Perſon and Authority, in the preſervation and defence of the true Religion and Liberties of the Kingdoms, that the world may bear witneſs with their conſciences of their loyalties, and that they have no thoughts or intentions to diminiſh His Majeſties juſt Power and Greatneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the <hi>Hiſtory of Independency</hi> hath diſcovered the practices of the <hi>Independent Junto,</hi> ſo this <hi>Appendix</hi> will diſcover their chief <hi>Confederate</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> namely the Marqueſs of <hi>Argyle;</hi> whoſe dealing with his Kindred, Friends, and Confederates mentioned in the following diſcourſe, will be a warning to all religious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, how they truſt ſuch an Apoſtate Covenanter, whoſe am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49589:3"/>and avarice hath ruined the KING, Church and State, or three flouriſhing Kingdoms. Although it may ſeem a paradox to many, I dare boldly aver, that <hi>Argile</hi> and his Faction in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laud,</hi> have been, and are the chief Malignants, Incendiaries, and evil Inſtruments, who have been the Ruiners of theſe three flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing Kingdoms, and the Authors of the blood ſhed in all of them as I hope by this following Diſcourſe will be made appear to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry impartial and unprejudicate Reader, who hath, or may have the certain knowledge of every particular when time ſhall ſerve. This <hi>Argile</hi>'s Father, after the marriage of his <hi>Engliſh</hi> Lady, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving turned <hi>Roman</hi> Catholique, and this his only Son by his firſt Lady being carefully educated by the Earl of <hi>Morton,</hi> by whoſe means he obtained the poſſeſſion of his Fathers whole Eſtate for a ſmal Penſion, and by his Majeſties ſpecial favour (for out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitting his pretended Title of <hi>Juſtice Generall of the Kingdom of Scotland</hi>) did obtain an Heritable Juſticiary of <hi>Argile, Lorn, Kintyre,</hi> and many of the Weſtern Iſles; which power he did execute with that cruelty; that he diſguſted all the Iſlanders, and Highlands of <hi>Scotland,</hi> who were never ſo tyrannized over by any of their Kings, till his Fathers death (ſtill fearing his return) he kept himſelf ſomewhat moderate for the engaging for the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, or keeping company ſometimes with thoſe that were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it; but his Father being dead, finding himſelf idolized by thoſe who had taken the managing of all affairs into their hands, and that by his power and policy he could prevail with them in any thing, to indear himſelf the more to that party, he did ſeem exceeding zealous for the Covenant, and pretending great fears from <hi>Ireland,</hi> (which the then Lord Deputy <hi>Strafford</hi> his Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and known averſeneſſe from the Covenant, did make the more eaſily to be believed) whereas the true cauſe of his fears was for the loſs of <hi>Kintyre,</hi> whereof he coſened his Brother long before his death) <hi>Iſla,</hi> and divers conſiderable Iſles which were and ought to be the poſſeſſions of the <hi>Macdonalds,</hi> and his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcreet provoking of <hi>Strafford,</hi> who in revenge of him did uſe very hardly all the <hi>Scots</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> who would not renounce the National Covenant of <hi>Scotland:</hi> he diſ-arming them, did Arm and Train many <hi>Iriſh,</hi> who (after his Head was off) ſhed ſo much bloud in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and upon pretence of diverſe of the <hi>Macdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalds (Argile</hi>'s own Tenants for the time) were acceſſary to the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49589:4"/>Plot, fearing his Judiciary power where he was both Judge and Party, they were inforced to flie to <hi>Ireland</hi> till their peace ſhould be made; to prevent which, he ſent their Wives and Children after them, took poſſeſſion of all their moveables, and placed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Tenants in their Room; but being grieved that <hi>Culkettough</hi> and his Sons, who had goodly Poſſeſſions, were not gone with the reſt, he cauſed cite them before the Council, as acceſſary to an Invaſion to be made by <hi>Antrim</hi> and ſome of their friends; which citation (as legal men and not guilty in the leaſt) they did obey, and after ſome dayes ſtay in <hi>Edinburgh</hi> (taking their walk daily before <hi>Argile</hi>'s door) they did humbly intreat his Secretary to plead for them, that they might have a ſpeedy hearing, ſince they were weary of their attendance; which the Secretary ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting the Lord <hi>Argile,</hi> returned them this anſwer, That ſince they had teſtified their obedience by their appearance, they might go home and behave themſelves civilly, not medling with their Rebellious friends, (as he was pleaſed to term them) and be ready upon any new citation, they ſhould be excuſed for that time: they did humbly thank his Lordſhip, and his Secretary, for this courteſie, and did preſently depart from <hi>Edinburgh</hi> towards their home; whereof my Lord (by his Spies upon them) having notice, did immediately convene the Council, and whereas in many dayes before (during their ſtay in Town) they could not be heard, that day they were firſt Called, and upon their not Anſwering, my Lord aggravating their Accuſation by their departure, occaſioned by his own and his Secretaries contriving, procures a Warrant to make them priſoners till they ſhould be Tried, and to ſeize upon their Eſtates; which out of his zeal to the Covenant (God knows) he did carefully perform, and made <hi>Culkettough</hi> and his two Sons Priſoners before they were half way at home; which <hi>Alexander Macdonald</hi> (afterwards Sir <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Macdonald</hi>) being fled to <hi>Ireland</hi> (having no valuable poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion to look to at home) did aſſociate himſelf with the <hi>Iriſh</hi> in the beginning of their Rebellion; but ſo ſoon as the <hi>Scots</hi> Army came over, he did apply himſelf to them, aſſuring them that he would do them faithfull ſervice againſt the <hi>Iriſh Rebels,</hi> if they would releaſe his old Father and his two Brethren, unjuſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained priſoners, or bring them to legal Trial, whereof having aſſurance given him, he brought with him two hundred gallant
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49589:4"/>men of his friends, and did more execution upon the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> than half of the <hi>Scots</hi> Army, their horſe being not able to follow through Bogs, and their Foot not ſo ſwift as the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and did in one morning bring in ſix or ſeven thouſand Cowes to the <hi>Scots</hi> Camp (the like booty they did never take at any one time before or ſince) for which good ſervice, the General did of new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage for his Father and Brethrens releaſment; but when the Committee of Eſtates had conſented, <hi>Argile</hi> did reverſe all, and fruſtrate the Generals promiſe: which <hi>Alexander Macdonald</hi> perceiving, ſaid no more (but well) I will yet cauſe my faithfull ſervice procure my fathers inlargement, and did continue without pay, or hope of pay, ſaving a very ſpare allowance of quarters, until <hi>Argile</hi> ſent over and cauſed him to be diſcharged of all quarters, to the grief of all the <hi>Scots</hi> Officers, who did well know what faithfull ſervice he had done, and was able to do them: ſo that meer neceſſity did inforce him to make his peace with the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> by whoſe help he did come over into <hi>Scotland,</hi> meerly to be revenged on <hi>Argile,</hi> and to relieve his Father, hoping the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of <hi>Scotland,</hi> would not blame him for ſuing the performance of what their General had promiſed unto him, intending no more til <hi>Montroſſe</hi> out of his deſire to be revenged on <hi>Argile</hi> did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force <hi>Alexander Macdonald</hi> to joyn his Majeſties Intereſt, as <hi>Montroſſe</hi> pretended, with the ſaid <hi>Macdonald,</hi> hoping he would find (as indeed he did) a great many diſcontented perſons to joyn with them, all which, or the moſt conſiderable, were parties and perſons wronged, oppreſſed, and ruined by <hi>Argile,</hi> as chiefly (beſides the forementioned Iſlanders and theſe <hi>Highlands</hi> that were under his laſh) the <hi>Athol</hi> men twice or thrice plundered by him; <hi>Montroſſe</hi> himſelf provoked by many well-known in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, which no noble heart could endure, as the death of Mr. <hi>James Stewart</hi> who was no Traitor either to King or Country ſave only to <hi>Argile.</hi> The Earl of <hi>Airly</hi> having his eſtate plundered and his Houſe thrown down in revenge of an antient quarrel amongſt their Predeceſſors, for the Earl of <hi>Airly</hi> having ſome Lands in the Bray of <hi>Augus,</hi> out of which <hi>Argile's</hi> men did many times drive Heards of Cattle, Sheep, and other Beaſts, for which the <hi>Ogilbee</hi> could have no remedy, theſe Thieves being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected by the Earl of <hi>Argile,</hi> by advice of his Lawyers he did Charge the Earl of <hi>Argile,</hi> that he ſhould find ſurety not to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49589:5"/>maintain or protect ſuch Out-lawes; but before he could obtain the ſame, he was obliged (according to the cuſtome of <hi>Scotland</hi>) to give his Oath, he did fear bodily harm from <hi>Argile,</hi> which he was unwilling to do; alleging, it were only a Beaſtly harm that he did fear, for if he would not protect thoſe that did ſteal his poor mens Beaſts, he was nothing afraid of his body. This tart Anſwer, after an age muſt (under colour of ſervice to the State) be ſo revenged.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Gourdons,</hi> divers of whom he betrayed under truſt, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of ſecuring his Nieces Portions that he was ingaged for, poſſeſſing himſelf of <hi>Badinoch</hi> and <hi>Lochabar,</hi> and plundering friends and foes indifferently in his marches too and fro, and the inexhauſtible treaſure of the <hi>Scots</hi> Exchequer muſt allow him eleven or twelve thouſand pound ſterlin for every Voyage: whereas his Breechleſſe Souldiery were well content with their Beef and Bannocks, and ſuch convenient plunder as the Country could afford: theſe (as I conceive) were the moſt conſiderable Forces <hi>Montroſſe</hi> ever had, unleſſe ſome that were through fear, compelled to yield for the time, ſo that the bloud-ſhed in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> by <hi>Montroſſe</hi> and <hi>Macdonald</hi> do properly fall upon <hi>Argiles</hi> ſcore, no other under Heaven having occaſioned both their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breakings; and all their partakers, who did ſee no other way to be revenged on him (that had made himſelf Maſter of all the Eſtate, having made <hi>Argile's</hi> quarrel their own) than by heaving at all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſpecious pretext of the Kings intereſt: which if God in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy had not prevented, they had almoſt effectuate through <hi>Argiles</hi> miſgovernment, wherein it is to be remarked, that when he was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrown by <hi>Montroſſe</hi> in <hi>Lochaber</hi> the ſecond of <hi>February,</hi> 1645. many of his friends being killed, and others taken, he who would not releaſe <hi>Culkettough</hi> for his Sons good ſervice, nor the Generals ingagement, or the Committee of Eſtates de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire (you muſt not ſpeak of Command) for Maſter <hi>James Hamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eon,</hi> a faithfull Miniſter of the Goſpel, who found more kindneſſe from <hi>Culkettough</hi> than from this Canibal Covenanter, is now content to releaſe all to get a poor Company of his Country-men, leaving the godly Miniſter in cruel bondage, whom <hi>Culkettough</hi> did releaſe upon his Paroll and promiſe to ſend him a Boy that was forgot behind.</p>
            <p>This religious Covenanter, out of his pious care for the educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49589:5"/>of his Siſter, in the true Religion as he pretended, did by His Majeſties ſpecial favour overthrow the laſt will and Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his mother-in-law, by getting himſelf made Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor in the room of him who was nominated therein, whereby he got the Gentlewoman his Siſters whole patrimony into his hands; but before he could prevail in this, His Majeſty did take ſpecial care that ſufficient Surety ſhould be given that the Will of the Dead ſhould be truly performed by payment of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective portions when they were Married, and ſufficient main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance until they were Married: the Elder whoſe Portion was Five thouſand pound ſterlin, is preſently ſent for, and one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pound or thereby given to a Gentleman for his ſecond Wife, the reſt (there being a clauſe <hi>that if any of them ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into Nunneries they ſhould only have</hi> 300 l. <hi>ſterlin for all</hi>) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kept ſo ſcarce of their due maintenance (the Gentleman who was ſurety, having advanced of his own above 1000 l. whereof he is not as yet repaid) were ſeduced to go to Monaſteries all ſave one, who is now ready to enter through his neglect; ſo this 12000 l. of his Siſters Portions (with the ruine of their Souls to boot) is a part of <hi>Argile</hi>'s wel-made purchaſe.</p>
            <p>The great care taken by the Earl of <hi>Morton</hi> for <hi>Argile's</hi> edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and preſervation both of his life from the crafty deſigns of a Step-mother, and recovery of his almoſt ruined Eſtate, was ſo well requited, that (notwithſtanding he hath the Earl of <hi>Morton's</hi> Daughter in his bed) in open Parliament he ſpake what became him not both of that noble Lords Perſon and Eſtate (only as he pretended, out of his zeal to the welfare of the Kingdom) whereas the truth is, it was meerly out of his ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to have that Honourable place conferred upon himſelf, which was intended by his Majeſty upon that noble Lord; but finding His Majeſty not inclinable that way, the next aſſault was, for one of his own name, a man truly well deſerving (for to ſay, better deſerving than himſelf, is no great praiſe) and if, his two much favouring of him do not ſtain his reputation, worthy to be beloved.</p>
            <p>Thus having ſhortly viewed <hi>Argile's</hi> religious carriage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Vaſſals and Tenants, Parents, Friends, and Allyes, Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Siſters, Neighbours, and fellow-Patriots, let us take a ſhort view of his Loyal carriage towards his Soveraign, and his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49589:6"/>due obſervation of the Solemn League and Covenant with his covenanted Brethren of <hi>England,</hi> and then let the impartial reader judge whether he be not ſuch as is affirmed in the propoſition, the greateſt incendiary in the three Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>It cannot be denied, but His Majeſty (as is mentioned before) did confer many great and Princely favours upon him at the Earl of <hi>Morton's</hi> deſire when he was Lord of <hi>Lorn,</hi> ſuch whereof as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired confirmation were approved and ratified in Parliament, His Majeſty being preſent, <hi>anno</hi> 1641. with the addition of the honour and title of Marqueſſe, and a full Penſion well paid ever ſince whoever want, together with (not only an <hi>Act of oblivion,</hi> but) approbation of all his tyrannical proceedings againſt the <hi>Athol</hi> men, the Earl of <hi>Aireley,</hi> and others, though not particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mentioned, yet as done in obedience of Orders from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of eſtates (obtained by his own procurement) therefore to be no further queſtioned.</p>
            <p>The firſt endeavour in requital of theſe and many other Royal favours was the entring in conſpiracy with certain his Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates (whom I forbear to name) to transform the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> into a free State like the Eſtates of <hi>Holland,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome truly noble Lords did abhor ſuch a diſloyal motion (after ſo many Acts of favour, witneſſing to all Poſterity his Royal bounty both to Church and State, whereof theſe chief Conſpirators taſted not a little) he did at that time forbear not ſo much to proſecute his deſign, as to conceal their Counſel from all theſe that had thoughts of Loyalty, though moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the true Religion and their Countrey, according to the Covenant. The <hi>Iriſh Rebellion</hi> breaking out, fearing his own ſtake if <hi>Antrim</hi> ſhould grow ſtrong, he procured one Regiment for himſelf, another for his Cozen <hi>Lawers,</hi> a third with the place of <hi>L. General</hi> for that moſt ungrate Gentleman the Earl of <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian</hi> (who was married to his neece and one of his Confidents, who was once heard ſay, <hi>That the 3 Kingdoms would never have peace ſo long as King</hi> CHARLES <hi>his head was on his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders:</hi> And yet it is only King CHARLES his favour that hath made him and Father exceed the eſtate of Gentlemen) with many other places to divers of their friends, intending a ful Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of <hi>Ireland</hi> (at leaſt) to baniſh <hi>Antrim</hi> and the <hi>Mackdonalds</hi> from thence, as he and his Predeceſſors had done many of them
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49589:6"/>out of <hi>Scotland,</hi> taking a gift from the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> of ſome of the Earl of <hi>Anerims</hi> Lands in <hi>Ireland,</hi> eſpecially the Iſland of <hi>Rachera;</hi> to the which, one of the forementioned Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments was ſent, and kept there a long time, ſo that all the three Kingdomes muſt be at the charge to maintain Armies and Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons for inlarging the Dominions of <hi>Argile.</hi> His next project, having begun his Confederacy in <hi>England,</hi> by ſhewing them the wayes to get money by Taxes, and Exciſe, 10. and 20. part, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in of Plate, voluntary Contributious, borrowing on the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Faith, tyrannizing over the Perſons and Eſtates of all that durſt be ſo bold as ſpeak againſt the illegal Orders, and all this Money in both Kingdoms to be imployed againſt His Majeſtie, whom their renewed Covenant did oblige them to defend, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving good opportunity to traffique betwixt under the pretence of Commiſſioners for the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> the reſt for the moſt part either his Creatures or Confidents; ſo that he ruled all the Council at home and abroad, ſending <hi>Lothian</hi> to <hi>France</hi> to have them brought in a <hi>Confederacy,</hi> abuſing his Majeſty by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing His Commiſſion for Treating concerning the keeping and preſervation of that ancient League betwixt <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> (begun in <hi>Charles the great's time,</hi> with <hi>Achaius</hi> King of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>) but the effect of the Treaty was to bring money to <hi>Argile,</hi> who, at that time when the Kingdom ſtood in much need of <hi>men,</hi> ſold five thouſand to the <hi>French</hi> to be under his Brother, (from whom he had, as formerly the Eſtate, ſo now the title of <hi>Kintire,</hi> and he muſt be Earl of <hi>Irwin,</hi> all the Intereſt be had there being by his <hi>quondum Tutor</hi> (now Slave) <hi>Barcley,</hi> his being ſometime Provoſt thereof) and the Chancellors Brother <hi>Lundie ſur France</hi> and <hi>Irwin</hi> had bad peny worths, although <hi>Argile</hi> made a good market for the men, like money truſted in a Juglers hand, were gone with a puff: thus you ſee how much both KING and Kingdome were obliged to him in this particular. But to come to the main point of the Conſpiracy, finding <hi>Scotland</hi> (although he had all the power of the Perſons and Eſtates in his hand) not pliable as yet to caſt off Monarchy, and imbrace Ariſtocracy, of whom (as affairs ſtood) none could be the chief Ruler but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he did imploy the Zealots of the Clergy to aſperſe thoſe who did oppoſe him (eſpecially ſome moſt faithfull and religious Noble men) as if they were fallen from their firſt love, turn ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49589:7"/>to the cauſe of Chriſt, had with <hi>Demas</hi> imbraced <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent world, and that <hi>Argile</hi> was the only man that ſtood in the gap; threatning out of their Pulpits all ſuch as would think or ſpeak evil of him; but when the State-juglers with their Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy-Impoſtors, could neither ſhake the Loyalty of the one, who were really for the Covenant and Monarchical Government, nor plaſter over the many fraudulent cheats of the Argathelian party, now become a moſt odious and heavy burthen to the Kingdom, haraſed and ruined from the one end to the other by him and his Armies on the one part, and <hi>Montroſſe</hi> and his Confederates on the other part, (<hi>Argyle,</hi> of the two, being the Kingdoms moſt cruel Enemy) was ſimulat humiliation, having the Church-men ſtil his friends, did reconcile himſelf to the other noble and loyal Patriots, by ſuffering them to take ſome ſhare of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the (by him) diſ-joynted State might by them be ſet in a right frame again, with a reſolution, when all things were right, to uſurp his wonted Authority, and follow his old trade of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throning his Majeſty, and cantonizing the Kingdome; but things falling out ſo, that one day at <hi>Nazeby,</hi> quelling the KINGS party in <hi>England;</hi> and one day at <hi>Phillipſhaugh,</hi> almoſt quieting <hi>Scotland;</hi> finding the Presbyterians in <hi>England</hi> inclinable to peace, and deſirous of his Majeſties re-eſtabliſhment according to the Covenant, he leaves them, and joyns Counſell with <hi>Say, Perpoint, Cromwell,</hi> and others of the Independent Junto, doing them that-Maſter piece of good ſervice. Firſt under colour of Loyalty and friendſhip to prevail with His Majeſty to return to the <hi>Scots Army</hi> then at <hi>Newark, Cromwel</hi> contributing a Paſſe to <hi>Hudſon,</hi> and <hi>Aſhburnham</hi> with a ſlack Guard, that His Majeſty might the more freely eſcape. Secondly, after many learned and loyal Speeches <hi>for Monarchy,</hi> the Kingdome of <hi>Scotlands</hi> intereſt in the perſon of the KING, and many Vows and Proteſtations both in private and publick, not to abandon His Majeſty with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his own conſent, contrary to all which, he and his Party did overthrow the Loyalty of that once famous Gentleman, Lieuten. General <hi>David Leſlie</hi> (who had deeply ſworn, and ingaged himſelf to His Majeſty, to convoy him ſafely into <hi>Scotland,</hi> or then to ſee His Majeſty peaceably ſetled in his throne in <hi>England</hi>) forcing him, and he perſwading and prevailing with the Souldiers to march away, leaving his Majeſty behind little better than (but
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49589:7"/>now an aſſured) Priſoner, and the whole power of the Sword in the hands of the Independents and Sectaries, to the ruine and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow of their Presbyterian friends in the City and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as the <hi>Hiſtory of Independency</hi> doth Witneſs, encouraging the Independent Party (by their Letters) to proceed in their dethro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Votes, and accuſation of his Majeſty, aſſuring them that no party from <hi>Scotland</hi> ſhall be able to hinder them in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings; but finding the body of the Parliament, and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Scotland</hi> to be ſenſible of the ruine of Religion and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchical Government if the Sectaries prevail, and their reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to adhere to their Covenant, and re-eſtabliſhing his Majeſty, being in fear their party ſhall not be able any longer to delude the Kingdom, or hinder the Army deſigned to come in for the vindication of the many breaches of the Solemn League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and the ſeveral Treaties betwixt the Kingdoms, they have ſolicited the Armies of Sectaries to come to their aſſiſtance, ſome of their Miniſters profeſſing in their Letters, <hi>They have no hope of ſafety, unleſs it be by means of this</hi> (rebellious) <hi>Army now in England,</hi> thereby endeavouring to make <hi>Scotland</hi> the ſeat of War.</p>
            <p>And if theſe troubles in <hi>Wales,</hi> and cutting Petitions from <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex, Kent, Surry,</hi> and <hi>Suſſex,</hi> had not hindered them, their reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution was to have ſent <hi>Cromwel</hi> thither, it being debated before he went to <hi>Wales,</hi> which of the two he ſhould take in hand; but the conſtant aſſurance they had from <hi>Argile,</hi> and thoſe accurſed Clergy-men that were bribed by <hi>Stephen Marſhal, That there was no fear of danger from</hi> Scotland <hi>in haſt,</hi> made them haſten to finiſh the enſlaving of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> and then they reſolve to conquer <hi>Scotland;</hi> which they conceive may be quickly done, having <hi>Argile</hi> and his Faction ſo firm to them, that although he would, neither he nor his Partners dare revolt from them, having received ſo much of their money, leſt they ſhould reveal more then he deſires ſhould be known; and as the Independents ſent their Emiſſaries through all Counties and Corporations, to get hands to Petitions <hi>for thanks to the Houſe for their dethroning Votes,</hi> ſo <hi>Argile</hi> and <hi>Marſhal</hi>'s Hirelings have been very active to get hands to Petitions in many Shires, Corporations, and Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Aſſemblies, for <hi>hindering the engagement againſt the</hi> rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Army of Sectaries, and the Independent Junto their Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates:</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:49589:8"/>whereas there is no intention againſt the Parliament, or Body of <hi>England;</hi> but <hi>to comply with all religious honeſt-hearted and loyal Subjects, who deſire that His Majeſty may be enlarged and brought to a Perſonal Treatie, whereby Peace and truth may be ſetled in the three Kingdoms;</hi> their chief pretences being, <hi>that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is not ſecured:</hi> the Religion now eſtabliſhed in <hi>Scotland</hi> was by Act of Parliament (His Majeſty preſent) ſo well ſecured, as the moſt religious Church-men, and moſt skilfull Lawyers could deviſe; if you have got <hi>New lights,</hi> and deſire any other Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion to be eſtabliſhed, vindicate His Majeſties Honour, and put up your Petitions to Him in an orderly way, and He may poſſibly vindicate you from the Yoke of Slavery which ſome of your ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannizing Clergy deſire to put upon you; The next is a wonderful increaſe of your fears by the great <hi>Truſts</hi> put upon ſuch perſons, of whom you have juſt cauſe of jealouſie to this Kingdom, and the Cauſe of God; though you do not ſpeak plain, your Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phletters do, and your Pulpit-Incendiaries to ſome purpoſe; you mean Duke <hi>Hamilton</hi> now Generall of the Forces, deſigned by the Kingdom and Parliament of <hi>Scotland for vindicating the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Nation, and revenging His Majeſties Captivity-upon that perfidious rebellious Army of Sectaries, and their adherents:</hi> what he did before the ſubſcribing of the Covenant ought not to be objected, (his moderation even then deſerving the honour and love of his Country) and ſince his ſubſcribing, malice it ſelf cannot tax him that he hath done any thing contrary to his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant or his Country; what <hi>Montroſſe</hi> doth aſperſe him with, that <hi>he hindred his intended invaſion of</hi> Scotland, and ſo conſequently His Majeſties Service; none of thoſe who ſtand for the Covenant who did think <hi>Montroſſe</hi> an enemy to the Covenant, and to his Country, ought to object this to my Lord Duke; whoſe tender care of the ſafety and welfare of his Country may evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear even in the relation of one of his moſt deadly enemies; and whereas his good advice for moderation was miſconſtrued by <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gile</hi> and his prevailing Faction on the one ſide, as if he had done things contrary to the Covenant; and by <hi>Montroſſe</hi> and his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates at Court on the other ſide, as if he had connived or been acceſſary to thoſe violent courſes againſt his Majeſty, which (God knows) he was not able at that time to hinder; his intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons being <hi>ſtill for Peace,</hi> and ſuch a Peace as might conſiſt with
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49589:8"/>the <hi>ſafety of Religion,</hi> and <hi>His Majesties honour;</hi> whereof he was very hopeful, being confident of His Majeſties propenſneſſe to Peace, and the intereſt he had in His Majeſties favour: but the watchfull malice of his enemies, and the enemies of Peace, did cunningly prevent his going about ſo good a work, making him Priſoner without His Majeſties knowledge, hindring by all means <hi>a meeting betwixt them,</hi> knowing that his Majeſties juſtice, and the Dukes innocency, would quickly make their calumnies to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh: what a ſad impriſonment did he indure, much heightned by the then impoſſibility of clearing his innocency to his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign (the loſſe of whoſe favour would be more bitter then a thouſand deaths) and his real intentions for the good of his Country, for whoſe cauſe he hazarded and ſuffered ſo much mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery and impriſonment? Yet this noble Dukes implacable and malitious enemies do further aſperſe him as a man of no Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a meer Polititian, and one that ſeeketh the ruine of his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, by the aſpiring to the Crown of <hi>Scotland:</hi> It would trouble the beſt Polititian, and the moſt Religious upon earth, in theſe diſtracting and diſtracted times, to diſtinguiſh rightly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>the duty we owe to Religion,</hi> and <hi>the duty we owe to our Prince,</hi> ſuppoſing them enemies; but the falſity of this ſuppoſition, (which hath miſled many thouſands, and been the ground of all our miſeries) being evident to the Duke, who had the honour to be educated and intimate with his Majeſty from his youth, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Majeſty to be a <hi>lover and honourer of the true Proteſtant Religion, a lover of juſtice and mercy, and a practiſer of all Chriſtian and moral virtues, and with a moſt munificent hand a royal Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor to himſelf and his Family.</hi> It may be asked, if it had been either piety or policy in the Duke to have kick'd off ſo loving and ſo liberal a Lord and Maſter, (although he had not been his Soveraign) or to have ingaged againſt his Country with any Party that for their own ends more then the good of their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns, were diſturbers of all moderate Counſels, ſo long as he had any hopes of Peace; eſpecially ſeeing ſo many ſad preſidents in both Kingdoms, where many powerfull Subjects, lovers of the true Proteſtant Religion, not joyning prudence with their loyalty and innocence, have cruſh'd them under the Load, &amp; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing eaſeth his Majeſties burthen, but rather increaſeth the ſame; all their wealth and power being now made inſtrumental to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49589:9"/>both KING and Kingdoms: the Duke's prudence having vindicated him from the ruine intended againſt him by his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and reſerved him (through Gods bleſſing) to vindicate his Loyalty by re-enthroning his Majeſty ſo ſoon as God hath ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled him with any power to do it. As for his Religion, it is known he is neither Popiſhly affected, nor a Sectary; but who hath ever been a profeſſor of the true Proteſtant Religion, a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler and Patron of all Godly men and honeſt Miniſters, even in the time of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> when few or none but himſelf durſt appear for them; if his judgement had not been overſwayed in ſome Star-Chamber ſentences, before he had that wiſdom and experience which he now hath, and long before he did take the Covenant; if he had been ambitious of popular applauſe, he had been more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown'd for his Religion, then for his Princes royall bounty; but wiſhing rather to be religious, then ſeem ſo, his favours were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in ſecret to many godly Miniſters, and his Majeſties honour and good chiefly aimed at in the beſtowing of them: and that you may take a ſhort view of his proceedings, as you have done of <hi>Argile</hi>'s, by comparing them, you will find who doth deſerve the Title of <hi>the moſt Religious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Duke</hi> Hamilton <hi>ſuffered his worthy Mother to enjoy, beſides her own Joynture, all his Eſtate, (whereby, indeed he loſt nothing, ſhe improving it much to his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage) hath helpt his Brother to a great eſtate, with Titles and Places of Honour and profit, ſuitable to his birth and worth; his Siſters, and now ſome of his Neices matched in the Nobleſt and beſt Families of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Duke had no quarrel with any ſave</hi> Montroſſe; <hi>the ground you heard, for croſſing his firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention for</hi> the Invaſion of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, to prevent the miſery and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49589:9"/>bloudſhed that he did foreſee was like to follow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Duke had no spoyls nor gifts given him ſince ever he ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Covenant (ſave the Title of DUKE) but hath been spoyled both himſelf and friends by thoſe that followed</hi> Montroſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Duke ſtands firm to his Covenant for the eſtabliſhed reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, loyal to his Prince for Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchical Government, faithfull to his Country againſt all forein Invaſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Duke acts nothing but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Laws eſtabliſhed, according to the Covenant, and the the duty of every good Subject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Duke</hi> Hamilton <hi>hath been of that temper to mediate for a wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grounded Peace, his Majeſties deliverance, and the Perſonal Treaty, being the only probable ways for ſetling the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and ſetling the power where it ought to be for the Honour and ſafety both of King and Subjects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Duke hath uſed, and is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all endeavours to Vindicate the oppreſſed Subjects in both Kingdoms, never changing Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, being always faithfull to all thoſe to whom he did profeſs love and friendſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:49589:9"/>1. Whereas <hi>Argile</hi> did in his Fathers life time b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing him to a Penſion, outed his Brother of his Eſtate, <hi>Kintyre,</hi> and ruined his Siſters by cheating them of their portions, and ſo enforcing them to go to Cloyſters.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Argile,</hi> for private quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels betwixt him and <hi>Montroſſe, Culkettough,</hi> and the <hi>Athol</hi> men, the Earl of <hi>Airely,</hi> and other, hath drawn much miſery and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49589:9"/>bloudſhed upon the Kingdom, whom he enforced to eſpouſe his quarrels.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Argile</hi> had enrich'd his Country with the ſpoyls of the Kingdom, and himſelf with the great treaſure beſtowed on him both by <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> which is well ſecured without the reach of an Impeachment.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Argile</hi> hath contrary to his Covenant, Duty and Allegiance, conſpired to extirpate Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chical Government, to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce foreinforces of Sectaries, to the utter overthrow of the eſtabliſhed Religion.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Argile</hi> hath overthrown all Laws, tyrannizing over the Lives, Liberties, and Eſtates of the Subjects.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Argile</hi> oppoſeth all ways of the Peace, &amp; ſetlement of the three Kingdoms, His Majeſties deliverance, and being brought to a Perſonal Treaty, leſt the power ſhould be taken out of his and his Confederates hands, whereby they oppreſs and ruine both King and Subject.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Laſtly, <hi>Argile</hi> hath betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his old friends the <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian party</hi> in both Kingdoms, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> in the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>London,</hi> not only ſuffering them to be made a prey to their enemies, but oſtructing their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:49589:10"/>
            <p>Let the impartial Reader now judge which of the two is moſt religious. As this oppoſition betwixt Duke <hi>Hamilton</hi> and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gile</hi> makes them both to appear what they are; ſo this following Parallel betwixt the <hi>Argathelian Faction</hi> and the <hi>Independent Jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> will ſerve for an eye-ſalve to cure the eye-ſight of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and let them ſee clearly how near they are to the brink of an intolerable and perpetual ſlavery.</p>
            <p>Argile <hi>and his Faction ſtiled by the</hi> Independents, the Godly party in <hi>Scotland,</hi> the reſt all Malignants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The like in</hi> England <hi>by the Army of Sectaries and Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Junto, above twenty millions ſhared amongſt them; whereof the Kingdom can never get accompt; all places of Honour and Truſt of</hi> England <hi>ſtill in the hands of thoſe that are engaged for, and with the Army of Sectaries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Cromwell <hi>and the army for the King in their firſt ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; but having inſlaved the City, inforced the Parliament to the dethroning Votes, and as not formerly acquainted therewith, gave thanks for them, and ſent their Emiſſaries to ſome ſeduced Counties and Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations to do the like.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Cromwell <hi>contributes a Paſſe to His Guides, ſlacking the guards, as he did the ſecond time, when he frighted him with a Plot from</hi> Hampton-Court <hi>to the</hi> Iſle of Wight, <hi>where he remains cloſe Priſoner.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:49589:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The blood ſhed in</hi> England <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der colour of</hi> juſtice <hi>in cold blood, calls aloud for vengeance; and the perfidious breaches of the Army of their promiſes to King, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and Country, is too too evident.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What the inſolent Army did, comming with Bayes in their hats when they inſlaved the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and riding in triumph through the City, by whoſe boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty they were made and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned an Army, will to their perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual infamy be regiſtred to all po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Army, and ſome others by their inſtigation, petition that the Kingdome may be ſetled without the King, and that Army continued to enſlave the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, especially the Presbyterian party, their Army being for Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Cromwell <hi>was ready to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, but got ſome other work for the time; and if God prevent it not, will now speedily be able to obey</hi> Argile's <hi>deſires; but if that fail,</hi> Argile <hi>ſhall have mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and ſend</hi> David Leſley to <hi>levy Forces abroad to work</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gile's <hi>ends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:49589:10"/>1. The Army of Sectaries in <hi>England</hi> (however formerly Preached and wrote againſt) now called by <hi>Argile's faction the hope of their ſafety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The heavy Taxes impoſed and continued upon <hi>Scotland</hi> by <hi>Argile</hi> and his Faction, and all the benefit thereof, and moſt part of the monies got from <hi>England,</hi> ſhared amongſt them, and no ſatisfactory accompt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Kingdom thereof.</p>
            <p n="3">3. All places of Honour and truſt uſurped by <hi>Argathelians</hi> (till of late) and the Army mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delled to maintain their Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Argile</hi> formerly (yet but ſeemingly) for Monarchy, now really againſt it, and all that deſire to aſſert it.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That Faction firſt betrays the King to come to the <hi>Scots</hi> Army, promiſing protection, and then moſt perfidiouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered Him up to the mercy of His moſt cruel Enemies.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:49589:10"/>6. <hi>Argile</hi> and his Faction have been moſt cruel to thoſe they call their <hi>Enemies,</hi> eſpecially in cold bloud; and perfidious to their friends, deſerting and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying them.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Argile</hi> when he had done miſchief, muſt have both thanks and reward; and like a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour, march through the Kingdom in triumph: a thing never granted amongſt the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Romans to triumph for a Victory in a Civil War.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Argile's</hi> Faction petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, That the Army intended for His Majeſties inlargement, and the relief of our Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Brethren ſhall not come in.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>Argile</hi> and his Faction deſires but five thouſand Horſe to aſſiſt them to ſubdue <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which muſt be turned a <hi>Province to the Kingdom of the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let this ſerve for a Caveat to the miſ-led and deluded Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants of the three Kingdoms not to truſt the <hi>fair promiſes or pretences of theſe ſeeming Saints,</hi> who have made the <hi>ſolemn League and Covenaat,</hi> (intended for preſervation of <hi>Religion, His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Honour, and the juſt Liberties of the Subject</hi>) to be the ruine of Religion, the diſhonour (ſo far as in them lieth) of His Majeſty
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49589:11"/>and the moſt abſolute enſlaving of all free Subjects, not to Kings or Princes, to Great men or Good men, but to the very ſcum and off-ſcouring of both Kingdoms; it being no ſmall grief to all that truly feared God, that ſo many of the reputed honeſt Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian party ſhould (out of baſe fear, or other by-reſpects) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply ſo long with theſe State-Juglers, the Clergy being moſt active, haſtning thereby their own and the Kingdoms miſery; for they may be well aſſured, if theſe Saints prevail, they muſt (as ſome of them have done already) turn their Coats once more, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Hirelings, and tongue-tied <hi>Tenants at will</hi> to <hi>their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of the Independency,</hi> or be kicked out of their <hi>fat Benefices,</hi> and poſſibly out of the Kingdom to prevent new Inſurrections a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, which they are cunning to procure, having the power in their hand to repreſs all that dare appear againſt them may be ruined, others by their example terrified, and their Saints may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the fatneſs of <hi>England;</hi> but I would ask theſe violent Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Presbyterian Party that are unwilling His Majeſty ſhould be brought ſpeedily to a <hi>Perſonal Treaty,</hi> what their <hi>Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies</hi> of <hi>Divines</hi> have been doing? for if that Confeſſion of Faith ſet out in <hi>England,</hi> approved of in <hi>Scotland,</hi> be agreeable to the truth of Gods word (as I know nothing to the contrary) why ſhould the chief Magiſtrate our dread Soveraign be any longer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar'd of his juſt dues? is He worſe then Infidel, that you will aſſiſt thoſe that deny His ſacred Majeſty that which they allow to Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del Magiſtrates? bluſh for ſhame, and repent in time, leſt as they change their Votes every day, according as the tide of their power ebbs and flows; ſo they may ſoon force you to repeal that Article concerning the chief Magiſtrate, or (like the gloſs of <hi>Orleans</hi>) put an expoſition upon it which deſtroyeth the text. <hi>God ſend us peace and truth, and preſerve His ſacred Majeſty, and his Poſterity, and confound the wicked counſels of all ſuch as are enemies to Peace, Truth, and Monarchy.</hi>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>—Si quid noviſtirectius iſtis,</l>
                  <l>Candidus imperti; Si non, his utere mecum.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:49589:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
